Can I get a show of hands --
هل ترفعون ايديكم
how many of you in this room have been on a plane in this past year?
كم شخص منكم استقل الطائرة خلال السنة الماضية؟
That's pretty good.
جميل جدا
Well, it turns out that you share that experience
حسنا، اتضح أنكم تتشاركون تلك التجربة
with more than three billion people every year.
مع أكثر من ثلاث بلايين شخص كل عام.
And when we put so many people in all these metal tubes
وعندما نضع الكثير من الناس في كل هذه الأنابيب المعدنية
that fly all over the world,
التي تدور حول العالم،
sometimes, things like this can happen
في بعض الأحيان، يمكن أن تحدث مثل هذه الامور
and you get a disease epidemic.
وتصاب بوباء.
I first actually got into this topic
لامرة مرة اهتممت بذلك الموضوع
when I heard about the Ebola outbreak last year.
عندما سمعت عن ظهور فيروس إيبولا العام الماضي.
And it turns out that,
واتضح أن،
although Ebola spreads through these more range-limited,
رغم ان فيروس إيبولا ينتشر أكثر من خلال طرق محدودة
large-droplet routes,
من خلال الرذاذ بشكل كبير
there's all these other sorts of diseases
كل الأنواع الأخرى من الأمراض
that can be spread in the airplane cabin.
يمكن أن تنتشر في مقصورة الطائرة.
The worst part is, when we take a look at some of the numbers,
أسوأ جزء هو، عندما نلقي نظرة على بعض الأرقام،
it's pretty scary.
مرعبة.
So with H1N1,
H1N1,
there was this guy that decided to go on the plane
كان هناك ذاك الرجل الذي قرر الذهاب على متن الطائرة
and in the matter of a single flight
وفي رحلة واحدة
actually spread the disease to 17 other people.
نشر المرض الى 17 شخص
And then there was this other guy with SARS,
شخص أخر مصاب بسارس
who managed to go on a three-hour flight
أستقل طائرة لثلاث ساعات
and spread the disease to 22 other people.
ونشر المرض الى 22 شخص .
That's not exactly my idea of a great superpower.
هذا ليست بالضبط فكرتي عن القوة العظمى
When we take a look at this, what we also find
عندما نلقي نظرة أخرى، ما نجده أيضا
is that it's very difficult to pre-screen for these diseases.
أنه من الصعب جدا فحص هذه الأمراض.
So when someone actually goes on a plane,
لذلك عندما يقوم شخص ما بالذهاب على متن طائرة،
they could be sick
من الممكن أن يكون مريضا
and they could actually be in this latency period
من المحتمل أن يكون في طور الكمون
in which they could actually have the disease
في الواقع يمكن أن يكونوا مصابين بهذا المرض
but not exhibit any symptoms,
ولكن لا تظهر أي أعراض،
and they could, in turn, spread the disease
ومن المحتمل نشرهم لذلك المرض
to many other people in the cabin.
الى أشخاص أخرين في المقصورة.
How that actually works is that right now
كيف يحدث هذا
we've got air coming in from the top of the cabin
لدينا هواء يأتي من الجزء العلوي بالمقصورة
and from the side of the cabin, as you see in blue.
وفي الجانب ايضا كما ترون بالأزرق .
And then also, that air goes out through these very efficient filters
ثم يخرج الهواء عبر فلاتر فعّالة جدا
that eliminate 99.97 percent of pathogens near the outlets.
التي تقضي على 99.97 في المئة مسببات الأمراض بالقرب من المنافذ .
What happens right now, though,
ماذا يحدث الأن،
is that we have this mixing airflow pattern.
لدينا الأن خلط في تدفق الهواء.
So if someone were to actually sneeze,
حتى إذا ما كان هناك شخص يعطس في الواقع،
that air would get swirled around multiple times
فالهواء يلفها عدة مرات
before it even has a chance to go out through the filter.
حتى قبل أن تحصل على فرصة لتمر عبر الفلاتر.
So I thought: clearly, this is a pretty serious problem.
مشكلة خطيرة جدا
I didn't have the money to go out and buy a plane,
أنا لا املك مال كافي لشراء طائرة.
so I decided to build a computer instead.
فقررت بناء حاسب عوضا عن ذلك
It actually turns out that with computational fluid dynamics,
في الواقع يتعامل مع ديناميكيات حاسوبية متدفقة
what we're able to do is create these simulations
ما نحن قادرون على فعله هو إنشاء هذه المحاكاة
that give us higher resolutions
هذا يعطينا دقة أعلى
than actually physically going in and taking readings in the plane.
من الذهاب جسديا وأخذ قراءات من الطائرة.
And so how, essentially, this works is you would start out
إذن، كيف، في الأساس، هذا يعمل وهل بدأت
with these 2D drawings --
مع هذا الرسم ثنائي الأبعاد
these are floating around in technical papers around the Internet.
تلك لأوراق التقنية تطوف حول الإنترنت.
I take that and then I put it into this 3D-modeling software,
أغتنمتها ووضعتها في برنامج نماذج ثلاثي الأبعاد ،
really building that 3D model.
ليبني مجسم ثلاثي الأبعاد .
And then I divide that model that I just built into these tiny pieces,
وبعد ذلك يقسم هذا النموذج القطع التي بنيتها الى قطع الصغيرة،
essentially meshing it so that the computer can better understand it.
وربطها معا حتى يستطيع الحاسب فهمها على نحو افضل .
And then I tell the computer where the air goes in and out of the cabin,
ثم أخبر الحاسب أين يدخل ويخرج الهواء
throw in a bunch of physics
عن طريق حسابات فيزيائية
and basically sit there and wait until the computer calculates the simulation.
واجلس منتظرا الحاسب ليقوم بحساباته
So what we get, actually, with the conventional cabin is this:
ما حصلنا عليه من المقصورة التقليدية هو :
you'll notice the middle person sneezing,
ستلاحظ الشخص في الوسط يعطس،
and we go "Splat!" -- it goes right into people's faces.
يصل الرذاذ لوجوه الناس.
It's pretty disgusting.
مثير جدا للاشمئزاز
From the front, you'll notice those two passengers
في المقدمة، سنلاحظ اثنين من المسافرين
sitting next to the central passenger
يجلسون بجوار االراكب بالوسط
not exactly having a great time.
ليس لديهم وقت ممتعا.
And when we take a look at that from the side,
وعندما نلقي نظرة من الجانب،
you'll also notice those pathogens spreading across the length of the cabin.
سنلاحظ أن مسببات الأمراض تنتشر عبر المقصورة
The first thing I thought was, "This is no good."
كان أول ما فكرت به "هذا ليس جيدا"
So I actually conducted more than 32 different simulations
لذا أجريت أكثر من 32 محاكاة مختلفة
and ultimately, I came up with this solution right here.
وفي نهاية المطاف، خطر لي الحل هنا.
This is what I call a -- patent pending -- Global Inlet Director.
هذا ما أسميه Global Inlet Director -براءة اختراع تنتظر المصادقة-
With this, we're able to reduce pathogen transmission
مع هذا، نحن قادرون على الحد من انتقال مسببات المرض
by about 55 times,
بنحو 55 مرة،
and increase fresh-air inhalation by about 190 percent.
وزيادة استنشاق الهواء النقي. بنحو 190 في المئة.
So how this actually works
كيف يعمل هذا
is we would install this piece of composite material
نود تثبيت هذه القطعة من المواد المركبة
into these existing spots that are already in the plane.
في هذه البقع الموجودة التي هي بالفعل في الطائرة.
So it's very cost-effective to install
لذلك فهي فعّالة جدا من حيث التكلفة
and we can do this directly overnight.
ويمكن القيام بذلك بين عشية وضحاها
All we have to do is put a couple of screws in there and you're good to go.
كل ما علينا القيام به هو وضع بضعة مراوح هناك،
And the results that we get are absolutely amazing.
والنتائج التي سنحصل عليها مذهلة.
Instead of having those problematic swirling airflow patterns,
بدلا من وجود تلك الإشكالية في أنماط تدفق الهواء،
we can create these walls of air
يمكن أن نخلق هذه الجدران من الهواء
that come down in-between the passengers
في المناطق الفاصلة بين المسافرين .
to create personalized breathing zones.
لخلق منطقة تنفس شخصية
So you'll notice the middle passenger here is sneezing again,
سنلاحظ المسافر الاوسط يعطس مجددا،
but this time, we're able to effectively push that down
ولكن هذه المرة يمكننا دفعها بفاعلية الى اسفل
to the filters for elimination.
الى الفلاتر للإزالة
And same thing from the side,
والشيء نفسه في الجانب،
you'll notice we're able to directly push those pathogens down.
ستلاحظ أننا دفعنا مسببات الأمراض لأسفل.
So if you take a look again now at the same scenario
أذا القينا نظرة مرة اخرى على نفس السيناريو
but with this innovation installed,
ولكن بعد تثبيت الأبتكار،
you'll notice the middle passenger sneezes,
ستلاحظ المسافر الأوسط يعطس،
and this time, we're pushing that straight down into the outlet
ولكن هذه المرة ندفعها الى المنافذ
before it gets a chance to infect any other people.
قبل ان تصيب شخص أخر .
So you'll notice the two passengers sitting next to the middle guy
لذلك ستلاحظ اثنين من الركاب يجلسون إلى جوار الرجل بالوسط
are breathing virtually no pathogens at all.
يتنفسون بلا مسببات للأمراض على الأطلاق .
Take a look at that from the side as well,
فلننظر من الجانب،
you see a very efficient system.
ترى نظام فعّال للغاية.
And in short, with this system, we win.
وباختصار، مع هذا النظام، فزنا.
When we take a look at what this means,
عندما نلقي نظرة على ما يعنيه هذا،
what we see is that this not only works if the middle passenger sneezes,
ما نراه هو أن هذا لايعمل فقط إذا كان الراكب الأوسط
but also if the window-seat passenger sneezes
ولكن ايضا اذا عطس الراكب بجوار النافذة
or if the aisle-seat passenger sneezes.
او حتى عطس الراكب بجوار الممر ،
And so with this solution, what does this mean for the world?
مع هذا الحل, ماذا يعنيه الى العالم؟
Well, when we take a look at this
حسنا, عندما نلقي نظرة على هذا
from the computer simulation into real life,
من محاكاة الحاسب للحياة الواقعية،
we can see with this 3D model that I built over here,
نرى من خلال النموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد الذي بنيته هنا
essentially using 3D printing,
باستخدام طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد،
we can see those same airflow patterns coming down,
يمكننا أن نرى نفس أنماط تدفق الهواء تأتي
right to the passengers.
مباشرة الى الركاب.
In the past, the SARS epidemic actually cost the world
في الماضي، كلف وباء السارس العالم
about 40 billion dollars.
حوالي 40 مليار دولار .
And in the future,
وفي المستقبل،
a big disease outbreak could actually cost the world
تفشي مرض كبير يمكن فعلا أن يكلف العالم
in excess of three trillion dollars.
ما يزيد على ثلاثة تريليونات دولار.
So before, it used to be that you had to take an airplane out of service
لذلك من قبل، كان عليك أن تأخذ طائرة خارج الخدمة
for one to two months,
لمدة شهر الى شهرين،
spend tens of thousands of man hours and several million dollars
تنفق عشرات الآلاف من ساعات الطيران وعدة ملايين من الدولارات
to try to change something.
محاولا تغير شيء.
But now, we're able to install something essentially overnight
ولكن الآن، ونحن قادرون على تثبيت شيء أساسي بين عشية وضحاها
and see results right away.
ونرى النتائج على الفور.
So it's really now a matter of taking this through to certification,
لذلك فالمهم حقا الآن هي مسألة الحصول على الموافقات
flight testing,
أختبار الطيران ،
and going through all of these regulatory approvals processes.
وتمر كل هذه العمليات عبر الموافقات التنظيمية.
But it just really goes to show that sometimes the best solutions
لكنها تظهر لنا في بعض الأحيان أن أفضل الحلول
are the simplest solutions.
هي أسهل الحلول.
And two years ago, even,
وحتى قبل عامين،
this project would not have happened,
هذا المشروع لم يحدث،
just because the technology then wouldn't have supported it.
لمجرد أن التكنولوجيا وقتها لم تكن داعمة لذلك
But now with advanced computing
ولكن الآن مع الحوسبة المتقدمة
and how developed our Internet is,
وكيف تطورت شبكة الإنترنت لدينا،
it's really the golden era for innovation.
انه حقا العصر الذهبي للابتكار.
And so the question I ask all of you today is: why wait?
وبالتالي فإن السؤال الذي أطرحه عليكم جميعا اليوم هو: لماذا الانتظار؟
Together, we can build the future today.
معا, يمكننا بناء المستقبل اليوم .
Thanks.
شكرا .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)